**HENG-CHANG CHEN** Update May 2<sup>nd</sup>, 2020

**Position** Postdoctoral Fellow

> Institut de Génétique Humaine (IGH) UMR 9002 CNRS - Université de Montpellier Laboratory of Molecular Virology

Dr. Benkirane Lab

141 rue de la Cardonille Montpellier - FRANCE

E-Mail: chen.heng-chang@igh.cnrs.fr

Personal website: http://chenhcinaki.wix.com/silence

I am molecular virologist and data scientist with over seven years of experience; I attempt to understand fundamental mechanisms involved in gene expression by using HIV as my model. To conquer this, I rely on a deep knowledge of human genomics and virology and collaborations with specialists. Using my skills involved in biotechnology and bioinformatics, I am capable of open a new branch of interdisciplinary research lines different from other standard HIV research laboratories.

#### **Education**

2008 - 2012	Dr. rer. nat. (Ph.D.)	Institute of Biology, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin	Berlin, Germany
2004 - 2006	M.Sc.	College of Medicine, National Taiwan University	Taipei, Taiwan
2000 - 2004	B.Sc.	College of Life Science. Tzu Chi University	Hualien. Taiwan

#### **Principle Positions Held**

09/2018-Currer	ntPostdoctoral sci	ientist Institut de Génétique Humaine (IGH)	Montpellier, France
2014-08/2018	Postdoctoral sci	ientist Centre de Regulació Genòmica (CRO	Barcelona, Spain
2011-2013	Lab Manager	Centre de Regulació Genòmica (CRO	Barcelona, Spain

#### Language

English | German | French | Spanish | Mandarin

I am fluent in spoken English and German (B1) and French (B1) and Mandarin (native speaker), full professional proficiency in reading and writing. I have a working knowledge of Spanish.

# Research and Creative Activities **Research Project**

2019-Current The impact of vc-cytokines on the selection of HIV integration sites, expression and reactivation (Supervisor: M. Benkirane, Institut de Génétique Humaine, Montpellier, France) We proof that HIV is prone to strengthen viral RNA expression and reactivation by the same vc-cytokines used for primary CD4+ T cells activation upon infection (Chen et al., manuscript under preparation).

2017-Current The chromatin landscape at the HIV-1 provirus integration site determines viral expression (Personal Research Collaboration with the lab of Dr. Debyser, KU Leuven, Leuven, Flanders, Belgium) We proof that LEDGINs, which are small molecule inhibitors of HIV integrase-LEDGF/p75 interaction enable to retarget HIV out of gene-dense and actively transcribed regions and consequently reduce viral RNA expression and increase the proportion of silent provirus (Vansant\*, G., H.-C. Chen\* et al., manuscript under revision; \*co-first authors).

The selection of HIV integration sites in the 3D genome (Supervisor: G. Filion, Centre de Regulació Genòmica, Barcelona, Spain)

We show the bias of HIV integration in the 3D genomic architecture: viruses tend to integrate in spatial proximity of super-enhancers in primary CD4+ T cells and in T cell cultures in vitro (Lucic\*, B., H.-C. Chen\* et al., 2019, \*co-first authors).

2013-2016 Position effects influence HIV latency reversal (Supervisor: G. Filion, Centre de Regulació Genòmica, Barcelona, Spain)

We successfully proof that HIV transcription is influenced by the local genomic context: viruses which integrate close to endogenous enhancers display the higher transcriptional level than those integrating far from enhancers (Chen et al., 2017).

2008-2011 Identification and characterization of a novel Salmonella gene product STM0029 (Supervisor:

L.H. Wieler & K. Tedin, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin, Berlin, Germany)

We reveal the importance of a novel Salmonella gene product STM0029 which contributes to the resistance to host antimicrobial peptide killing (**DOI: 10.18452/16658**).

2004-2006 Characterization of a putative function of the two-component system ScnRK in

Streptococcus mutans (Supervisor: J.S. Chia, National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan)

We identify the function of S. mutans two-component system ScnRK involved in the resistance of hydrogen peroxide and murine macrophage killing (**Chen et al., 2008**).

#### Research Experience

09/2018-Currer	Montpellier, France	
2014-7/2018	Postdoctoral fellow, Centre de Regulació Genòmica (CRG)	Barcelona, Spain
1/2017-2/2017	Visiting scientist, CNRS UMR7216, Université Paris 7	Paris, France
SS 2014	Visiting scientist, ITZ, Ecology & Evolution, TiHo Hannover	Hannover, Germany
SP 2011	Visiting researcher, Institute of Food Research	Norwich, U.K.
2008-2011	Ph.D. fellow, Institute of Biology, Humboldt-Universität zu Berlin	Berlin, Germany
W 2008	Visiting student, Friedrich-Alexander-Universität Erlangen-Nürnberg	Erlangen, Germany

# **Biotechnology**

B-HIVE | Illumina sequencing | Oxford Nanopore sequencing | Hi-C & 4C | CRISPR/Cas9 | ATAC-seq | clinical/blood samples (primary cells isolation) | BSL3 lab

#### Computing ability

R: Advanced knowledge

Docker | Python | Linux | awk | SPSS: Working knowledge

GitHub: https://github.com/HCAngelC

I have experience in analyzing different types of Big Data, including RNA-seq data, ChIP-seq data, Gene Ontology analysis and Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA). I set up the analysis pipeline for Oxford Nanopore long-read sequencing data.

# Certifications

- » Machine Learning with R Level 1 issued by IBM (<a href="https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/b3728109-db25-49d3-8f4e-1416547fe11a/linked">https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/b3728109-db25-49d3-8f4e-1416547fe11a/linked</a> in)
- » Python for Data Science issued by IBM (https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/5004f08c-4077-4d2b-9b6b-212bbfe57518/linked in profile)
- » Statistics 101 issued by IBM (<a href="https://courses.cognitiveclass.ai/certificates/08d0c21d4ac34ad7b2d060032989c821">https://courses.cognitiveclass.ai/certificates/08d0c21d4ac34ad7b2d060032989c821</a>)

# **Research Awards and Grants**

3/2018 Marie Sklodowska-Curie Actions Proposal Seal of Excellence 786552 - HIV-MAP

2/2017 EMBO Short-term Fellowship ASTF699-2016

2016 Awarded student talk in the 13th Horizons in Molecular Biology Symposium, Göttingen, Germany

2008-2011 Ph.D. fellowship funded by German Research Foundation (DFG)
2004 Student exchange program, Colorado College, Colorado, USA
2003 Bio-prize awarded by the Tzu Chi University, Taiwan (R.O.C.)

# **Peer Reviewed Publications**

Please see the list of peer reviewed publications in the final page.

# **Cover Image Publications**

2015 Natural Product Reports Vol. 32, No. 1, January Molecular Cell Vol. 52, Issue 5, 12 December

# **Publications and Press**

Scientific Image | Imatge científica - HIV Infection | Infecció per VIH El-lipse, NÙM. 66, 2013 (Parc Recerca Biomèdica Barcelona monthly newspaper)

# **Image Credits**

iCLIP: Genomic views of protein-RNA interactions EMBO Practical Course

# **Acknowledgements**

Martinez, J.P., F. Sasse, M. Brönstrup, J. Diez and A. Meyerhans. 2015. Antiviral drug discovery: broad-spectrum drugs from nature. Nat. Prod. Rep. DOI: 10.1039/C4NP00085D

Professional Organizations and Activities
Momborchine and Affiliations

wembersnip	s and Amiliations
2013-2018	Verband Biologie, Biowissenschaften & Biomedizin in Deutschland (VBIO e.V.)
2013-2018	Vereinigung für Allgemeine und Angewandte Mikrobiologie (VAAM)
2015-2016	IAS (International AIDS Society)
2014-2015	SciArt Center (http://www.sciartcenter.org)
2010-2013	Gesellschaft für Biochemie und Molekularbiologie (GBM)

# **Service to Professional Organizations**

2016	Organization committee of the CRG postdoctoral Retreat	Barcelona, Spain
2014	Organization committee of the V CRG postdoctoral Symposium	Barcelona, Spain

# Competitively Invited Talks and Oral Presentations

Invited	Talks Talks	
6/2018	Fluctuations in HIV expression and the host genome (Hosted by DEBYSER, 2	Z. & Francqui Foundation)
	Workshop on "Nuclear architecture and retroviral integration"	Leuven, Flanders, Belgium
9/2017	HIV expression, PEV and 3D genome (Hosted by PARISSI, V. & EMILIANI, S	5.)
	6th International Conference on Retroviral Integration	Bordeaux, France
3/2017	HIV latency, chromatin and genome architecture (Hosted by LEE, CK.)	
	College of Medicine, National Taiwan University	Taipei, Taiwan
2/2017	HIV latency and genome evolution in reservoirs	
	METU Evolutionary Biology Conference, Middle Fast Technical University	Ankara Turkey

1/2017	Chromatin and HIV	latency (Hosted by DEFOSSEZ, PA.)	
	CNRS UMR7216,	Université Paris 7	Paris, France

2016	HIV expression and genome architecture	
	Curs "Les noves 'Bio' II", Centre for Genomic Regulation (CRG)	Barcelona, Spain

2015	Open the Chamber of Secrets of HIV-1 Latency	
	L'Institut d'Investigacions Biomèdiques August Pi i Sunyer (IDIBAPS)	Barcelona, Spain

Oral Pr	resentations	
06/201	7 Faculty-selected talks: The invisible world of HIV latency in the human genome	
	8 <sup>th</sup> CRG Postdoctoral Symposium	Barcelona, Spain
2016	Visualisation of HIV latency by the new technology Barcoded HIV Ensembles	
	13th Horizons in Molecular Biology Symposium	Göttingen, Germany
2015	Visualisation of HIV-1 latency on chromatin landscapes	
	6 <sup>th</sup> CRG Postdoctoral Symposium	Barcelona, Spain
2014	Lighting talk: Visualisation of HIV-1 latency	
	The 2 <sup>nd</sup> EMBO Conference Visualizing Biological Data (VIZBI)	Heidelberg, Germany
2010	A novel orphan <i>phoPQ</i> -independent regulator influences <i>Salmonella</i> intracellular	
	survival and antimicrobial peptides resistance	
	National Symposium on Zoonoses Research	Berlin, Germany

# Teaching and Mentoring

Mentoring	
SP 2017 Gerlinde VANSANT (FWO grant), CRG	Barcelona, Spain
SS 2014 Oguzhan BEGIK (Erasmus programme), CRG	Barcelona, Spain
SP 2012 Fundació Catalunya E <sup>2</sup> C <sup>3</sup> -Centre Recerca practical course, CRG	Barcelona, Spain
SP 2010 Molecular microbiological manipulation/master student, Free University	Berlin, Germany
SP 2009 Molecular microbiological manipulation/bachelor student, Free University	Berlin, Germany

# Workshop

SP 2015 Art, Science and Data Visualisation, CRG PhD retreat	Castellar de n'Hug, Spain
--	---------------------------

# **Informal Teaching and talks**

2016	CRG summer school	Barcelona, Spain
2013	Lab Workshop assistant, CRG Teaching Day	Barcelona, Spain
2012	Lab introducer, CRG Open Day	Barcelona, Spain

# Peer Reviewed Publications 2020

- » Machida, S., D. Depierre, **H.-C. Chen**, S. Houssier, G. Petitjean, C. Doyen, M. Takaku, O. Cuvier and M. Benkirane. 2020. Exploring histone loading on HIV DNA reveals a dynamic nucleosome positioning between unintegrated and integrated viral genome. *PNAS*. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1913754117 (Q1; IF: 9.58)
- » Lucic, B.\*, **H.-C. Chen**\*, M. Kuzman\*, E. Zorita\*, J. Wegner, V. Minneker, W. Wang, R. Fronza, M. Schmidt, and R. Stadhouders, V. Roukos, K. Vlahovicek, G. Filion and M. Lusic. 2019. Spatially clustered loci with multiple enhancers are frequent targets of HIV-1. *Nat. Communications.* doi: 10.1038/s41467-019-12046-3 (\*Co-first authors) (Q1; IF: 11.878; citation: 3) 2018
- » Abner, E., M. Stoszko, L. Zeng, **H.-C. Chen**, A. Izquierdo-Bouldstridge, T. Konuma, E. Zorita, E. Fanunza, Q. Zhang, T. Mahmoudi, M.-M. Zhou, G. Filion, and A. Jordan. 2018. A new quinoline BRD4 inhibitor targets a distinct latent HIV-1 reservoir for re-activation from other 'shock' drugs. *J Virol*. doi: 10.1128/JVI.02056-17. (Q1; IF: 4.324; citation: 10)
- » Chen, H.-C.\*, E. Zorita, and G. Filion\*. 2018. Using Barcoded HIV Ensembles (B-HIVE) for single provirus transcriptomics. *Curr Protoc Mol Biol.* doi: 10.1002/cpmb.56 (\*Corresponding authorship) (Q1; citation: 3)
- » Lucic, B.\*, **H.-C. Chen**\*, M. Kuzman\*, E. Zorita\*, J. Wegner, V. Minneker, V. Roukos, W. Wang, R. Fronza, M. Schmidt, M. Benkirane, R. Stadhouders, K. Vlahovicek, G. Filion and M. Lusic. 2018. Spatially clustered loci with multiple enhancers are frequent targets of HIV-1. 2018. Spatially clustered loci with multiple enhancers are frequent targets of HIV-1. *BioRxiv*. doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/287896. (\*Co-first authors)
- » Chen, H.-C., J.P. Martinez, E. Zorita, A. Meyerhans, and G. Filion. 2017. Position effects influence HIV latency reversal. *Nat Struct Mol Biol.* doi: 10.1038/nsmb.3328. (Q1; IF: 12.109; citation: 56)
- » Corrales, M., P. Cusco, D.R. Usmanova, **H.-C. Chen**, N.S. Bogatyreva, G.J. Filion, and D.N. Ivankov. 2015. Machine learning: how much does it tell about protein folding rates? *PLoS One*. doi:10:e0143166. (Q1; IF: 2.776; citation: 12)

#### 2008

» Chen, P.M., **H.-C. Chen**, C.T. Ho, C.J. Jung, H.T. Lien, J.Y. Chen, and J.S. Chia. 2008. The two-component system ScnRK of *Streptococcus mutans* affects hydrogen peroxide resistance and murine macrophage killing. *Microbes and Infection*. doi:10:293-301. (**Q2**; IF: **2.669**; citation: **32**)

# Conference publications

» Vansant, G., **H.-C. Chen**, E. Zorita, G. Filion, and Z. Debyser. 2019. HIV integration site selection affects transcription. **CSHL retroviruses**. Cold Spring Harbor, New York.

# Manuscript under revision

» Vansant\*, G., **H.-C. Chen**\*, E. Zorita, Trejbalová, K., Miklík, D., G. Filion, and Z. Debyser. 2020. The chromatin landscape at the HIV-1 provirus integration site determines viral expression. *Nucleic Acids Research*. (\*Co-first authors)